Register of the Richard Paul Mitchell collection
Hoover Institution Archives
- Organizations File, 1967-1983, undated (Boxes 39-40)
  - Ad Hoc Committee for Academic Freedom, 1983 May 5 (Box-folder 39: 3)
    Contains a letter from the committee with a copy of an ad they ran listing the names of individuals who supported their campaign for academic freedom on the West Bank and Gaza. Richard Mitchell's name is listed.
  - Ad Hoc Lebanon Emergency Committee, 1982 (Box-folder 39: 4)
  - American Arab Affairs Council, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 39: 5)
  - American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee (ADC), 1981-1983 (Box-folder 39: 6-10)
    Contains mailings and publications produced by the ADC, including copes of the ADC Backgrounder, ADC Issues, and ADC Reports. Also included is the booklet Eyewitness to Israel's Terror in Lebanon: Summer 1982.
  - The American Committee for Human Rights in Egypt, undated (Box-folder 39: 11)
    Contains a letter from the organization titled, "Repression in Egypt: What U.S. Aid to Egypt Supports."
  - American Professors for Peace in the Middle East, 1973 (Box-folder 39: 12)
    Contains one bulletin discussing current issues in the Middle East.
  - Americans for Middle East Understanding, Inc., undated (Box-folder 39: 13)
    Contains a mailing titled "Israeli Settlements in the Occupied Territories."
  - Association of Arab-American University Graduates, Inc. (AAUG), 1982-1983 (Box-folder 39: 14)
    Contains a letter from AAUG president, as well as AAUG newsletters that discuss topics such as the 1982 Lebanon War and the Sabra and Shatila massacre, in addition to AAUG news.
  - Moslem Students Society (U.S.A.), 1981-1982 (Box-folder 40: 1-3)
    Contains organizational statements, newsletters, bulletins, and other miscellaneous publications. Includes some publications in Arabic.
  - The Organization of Arab Students, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 40: 4)
    "An educational, cultural, non-profit organization promoting better American-Arab understanding." Contains material in English and Arabic.
  - People's Mojahedin Organization of Iran (PMOI), 1981 (Box-folder 40: 5)
    Contains news bulletins of the PMOI, an exiled Iranian movement that opposes the Islamic Republic of Iran. The bulletin is described as "a weekly bulletin presenting the important political events taking place in Iran, and a brief account of PMOI stances." Also includes a copy of a letter titled, "Death to the Khomeini's Regime, Long Live Freedom" from the Supporters of the PMOI.
  - Revolutionary Communist Youth Brigade (Ann Arbor chapter), undated (Box-folder 40: 6)
    Contains a letter urging people to join with the group in organizing an "All-Michigan Iran Day" to consist of a one day teach-in on the subject of Iran.
- Printed Matter, 1950-1983, undated (Boxes 40-43)
  Contains periodicals, reports, booklets, books, and other printed matter mainly relating to Middle Eastern and Islamic issues from the mid to late 1970s. Arranged by type and then alphabetically by author or title.
  - Periodicals, 1967-1983
    - Al-Ahram Iktisadi, 1983 August 22 (Box-folder 40: 7)
    - Al-'Asifah, number 8, 1967 October (Box-folder 40: 8)
      Produced by the Palestinian group Fatah.
    - Al-Da'wa, 1976, 1981 (Box-folder 40: 9-15)
      Monthly publication of the Muslim Brotherhood. Contains numbers 1-4 from 1976 and numbers 57-59 from 1981. See also Jarīda in The Society of the Muslim Brothers Research Materials series for earlier editions.
    - American Near East Refugee Aid (ANERA) Newsletter, 1980-1982 (Box-folder 40: 16-18)
      Scope and Contents noe
      Contains numbers 52, 54, and 59.
    - Cairo Today, 1983 August (Box-folder 40: 19)
    - Current History, 1980 April (Box-folder 40: 20)
    - Islam Centennial Fourteen Newsletter, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 40: 21-24)
      Contains volume 3, numbers 1, 3, and 5 and volume 4, number 1.
    - Islamic Horizons, 1983 May-October (Box-folder 40: 25-29)
      Contains volume 7, numbers 4-10.
    - Islamic Studies, American Institute of Islamic Studies, 1973-1974, 1976 (Box-folder 40: 30-32, Box-folder 41: 1)
      Contains volume 1, numbers 3 and 4 and volume 2, numbers 4 and 5.
    - The Journal, The Muslim World League, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 41: 2-5)
      Contains volume 5, numbers 3 and 5; volume 6, number 2; and volume 7, number 1.
    - Lebanon News, 1982-1983 (Box-folder 41: 6-11)
      Contains volume 5, numbers 7, 8, and 10; volume 6, number 2; and special issues 2 and 3.
    - Leviathan, 1978, 1980 (Box-folder 41: 12-13)
      Contains issues from Spring 1978 and Fall 1980.
    - Mahjubah, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 41: 14-19)
      Contains volume 1, numbers 5-12.
    - Middle East Research and Information Project (MERIP) Reports, 1978-1980 (Box-folder 41: 20-23)
      Now published under the name Middle East Report. Contains number 71, "Iran: Crisis Update; Trade Unions; Agricultural Dependence;" number 72, "After Camp David: Egypt Confronts Peace;" number 75/76, "Iran in Revolution;" and number 88, "Iran's Revolution: The First Year."
    - New Muslim Outlook, 1981 (Box-folder 41: 24-26)
      Contains volume 1, numbers 1-4. Also includes correspondence.
    - Replica's Digest, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 41: 27)
      Each publication contains English summaries of articles from Arabic language newspapers, in particular summaries of the editorials published in Al-Medina by the managing editor, Mohammad Salahuddin. Includes six issues.
    - US Bureau of Public Affairs publications, 1974-1980
      - Department of State, 1974-1980
        - Bulletin Reprints, 1977, 1979 (Box-folder 41: 28)
          Contains two bulletins containing the "official monthly record of United States foreign policy," one from July 1977 and one from October 1979.
        - Current Policies, 1975-1976, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 41: 29-31)
          Topics include: foreign military sales, Palestine, the Middle East, human rights policy, energy, developing countries, the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan, the United Nations, and Iran hostage rescue attempts in April 1980.
        - Gist, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 41: 32)
          "A quick reference aid on U.S. foreign relations primarily for Government use. Not intended as a comprehensive U.S. policy statement." Contains three issues from September 1975, March 1976, and May 1976.
        - News releases, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 42: 1-2)
          Topics include: energy, the Middle East, Arab-Israeli relations, relations with Iran, international commodity policy, the United Nations, North Africa, oil, the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD), and human rights.
        - Selected Documents, 1975, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 42: 3-9)
          Contains issue number 3, "U.S. International Energy Policy, October 1973-November 1975;" number 8, "Reform and Restructuring of the U.N. System;" number 11, "The Egyptian-Israeli Peace Treaty;" number 12A, "SALT II Agreement;" number 13, "Vienna Summit;" number 14, "Iran: U.S. Hostage Case to World Court;" and number 15, "World Court Rules on Hostage Case."
        - Special reports, 1975-1976, 1980 (Box-folder 42: 10-14)
          Contains issue number 12, "U.S. Policy in the Middle East, December 1973-November 1974;" number 16, "Encouraging Investment in Domestic Energy: Minimum Safeguard Price;" number 17, "Toward a Strategy of Interdependence;" number 25, "Conference on International Economic Cooperation (CIEC);" and number 70, "Soviet Invasion of Afghanistan."
        - Speeches, 1976-1979 (Box-folder 42: 15-16)
          Contains speeches from various members of the Department of State. Topics include: Africa, peace in the Middle East, Third World countries, energy, human rights, and political change.
        - Statements, 1977 (Box-folder 42: 17)
          Contains two statements titled "Problem of International Terrorism" and "Human Rights Policy Review."
      - Secretary of State, 1974-1979
        - Interviews, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 42: 18)
          Contains interviews with Secretary of State Cyrus Vance on the television shows Meet the Press and the MacNeil-Lehrer Report, in which he discusses current issues in the Middle East.
        - Press conference summaries, 1975-1978 (Box-folder 42: 19)
          Topics include: detente, peace in the Middle East, oil, Israel, United Nations vote on Zionism, the European Economic Summit, terrorism, Africa, Lebanon, SALT, Moscow radiation of US Embassy, Italy, arms control, human rights, and China.
        - Speeches, 1974-1979 (Box-folder 42: 20-22)
          Topics include: the energy crisis, Africa, foreign policy, relations with Israel, and Sahel development.
        - Statements, 1975-1978 (Box-folder 42: 23-24)
          Topics include: peace in the Middle East, Egypt-Israel relations, Africa, Europe, Latin America, policy regarding nuclear weapons, the proposed sale of Airborne Warning and Control Systems (AWOCS) to Iran, and foreign assistance programs.
  - Memo, "Islam and U.S. Public Diplomacy,", undated (Box-folder 42: 25)
    Photocopy of a interim staff draft of a memo from the USICA (most likely the United States International Communications Agency).
  - Transcript, "Khomeini Takes Iran," The MacNeil/Lehrer Report, 1979 February 13 (Box-folder 42: 26)
    Transcript of an episode featuring Jim Lehrer, Shahriar Rouhani (Khomeini representative), Stephen Solarz (Democratic Representative), Charlayne Hunter-Gault (correspondent), and Eric Rouleau ( Le Monde magazine).
  - Reports, 1950, 1977-1979
    - The International Energy Situation: Outlook to 1985, CIA report, 1977 April (Box-folder 42: 27)
    - A Report to the National Security Council by Executive Secretary on United States Objectives and Programs for National Security, photocopy, 1950 April 14 (Box-folder 42: 28)
    - Strategic Arms Limitation Talks (SALT) II reports, 1979 (Box-folder 42: 29)
      Contains material produced by the Department of State, including a special report and a revised special report on SALT II, as well as a glossary of terms and a document titled "SALT II: The Reasons Why."
  - Booklets, 1974-1983
    - Department of State, 1974-1976
      - America's Purposes in an Ambiguous Age, 1974 (Box-folder 42: 30)
      - Energy and International Cooperation, 1975 (Box-folder 42: 31)
      - Foreign Policy and the Department of State, 1976 (Box-folder 42: 32)
      - United States Chiefs of Mission 1973-1974, supplement (Box-folder 42: 33)
      - United States Foreign Policy: An Overview, 1975 May (Box-folder 42: 34)
      - United States Foreign Policy: An Overview, 1976 January (Box-folder 42: 35)
    - Middle East Institute, Middle East Problem Paper, number 25, 1983 January (Box-folder 43: 1)
      Contains "Egypt Under Mubarak" by Mohamed Hakki.
    - Realities of the Middle East: A Report by Senator George S. McGovern to the Committee on Foreign Relations, United States Senate, 94th Congress, 1975 (Box-folder 43: 2)
    - Shariati, Ali, Civilization and Modernization (photocopy), 1979 (Box-folder 43: 3)
    - Thurat Zafar (Dhofar Rebellion), 1973 (Box-folder 43: 4)
  - Books, 1968-1981, undated
    - 'Abd al-Raḥmān, The Betrayal of Iran, 1979 (Box-folder 43: 5)
    - Afghani, Jamal al-Din, 1981 (Box-folder 43: 6)
      In Arabic. Title translates to "In the Writings of the Islamic Renaissance."
    - Middle East Arms Sales Proposals: Hearings Before the Committee on Foreign Relations, United States Senate, 95th Congress, 1978 (Box-folder 43: 7)
      Contains photocopies of pages 132-137.
    - Nadvi, Sayyid Sulaiman, The Living Prophet, translated by Sayeed-ul-Haq (photocopy), 1968 (Box-folder 43: 8)
      Photocopy of a translation of Nadvi's "Kutbat-e-Madras," a series of eight lectures delivered at Madras in 1925.
    - Osman, Mohammed Fathi, Alssalafiat fi almujtamaeat al'iislamiat almueasira, undated (Box-folder 43: 9)
      Title translates to "Salafism in Contemporary Islamic Societies." Contains a photocopy of pages 259-310.
    - The Palestinian Issue in Middle East Peace Efforts: Hearing Before the Special Subcommittee on Investigations of the Committee on International Relations, House of Representatives, 94th Congress, 1975 (Box-folder 43: 10)
    - Priorities for Peace in the Middle East: Hearings Before the Subcommittee on Near Eastern and South Asian Affairs of the Committee on Foreign Relations, United States Senate, 94th Congress, 1975 (Box-folder 43: 11)
    - Rothermund, Dietmar, ed., Islam in Southern Asia: A Survey of Current Research (photocopy), 1975 (Box-folder 43: 12)
    - US Arms Control and Disarmament Agency, World Military Expenditures and Arms Trade 1963-1973, 1975 (Box-folder 43: 13)
- Oversize Material, 1973-1983 (Box 50)
  Contains newspapers and magazines published in the Middle East, the US, and Nigeria. Also included is a Syrian poster warning against the Muslim Brotherhood and a poster for a BBC radio show on Islam. Material in Arabic and English. Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Al-Alam, 1974 January 21
  - Al Anbaa', 1973 May 23
    Contains pages 5-8 only.
  - Arab Times, 1979 November 26
    Daily English-language newspaper published in Kuwait.
  - Al-Ard, 1978, 1980
    Contains issues from December 12, 1978; March 4, 1980; and March 11, 1980.
  - Daily Sketch, 1973
    Daily newspaper from Nigeria. Contains issues from June 3, 1973 and June 5, 1973. The Sunday publication is titled the Sunday Sketch.
  - Daily Times, 1973
    "The Independent newspaper" published daily in Nigeria. Contains issues from June 2, 3, and 5, 1973.
  - The Egyptian Gazette, 1983 September 6-8
  - Al-Fajr al-Jadid, 1978 July, 1980 February
  - Al Gomhuria, 1976 March 2
    Egyptian daily newspaper owned by the state. Front page contains a handwritten note to Mitchell regarding an article about the arrest of Jalal al-Din al-Hamamsy, an influential journalist.
  - Headlines, number 3, 1973 June
    "Stories that made headline news." Printed in Nigeria.
  - International Herald Tribune, special issue "Focus on Turkey,", 1977 May
  - "Islam in the Modern World" poster, 1978
    Poster for a BBC Radio 3 documentary series beginning May 6, 1978.
  - Iran Voice, 1979-1980
    Published by the Embassy of the Islamic Republic of Iran in Washington, D.C. Contains numbers 13-18 (August 27-October 1, 1979) and 22 (January 21, 1980) of volume 1.
  - Al-Lewaa al-Islami, 1983 January 9
  - Al-Madinat al-Adby, 1978 March
    Contains two copies of the same issue.
  - Al-Majallat al-Riadia, 1983 August 17
  - Al-Muntajun, 1978 December
  - Monday Morning, volume 8, number 364, 1979 June 11-17
    A Lebanese newspaper printed in Beirut. Includes an interview with Mustafa Khalil, Prime Minister of Egypt.
  - The Nigerian Observer, 1973 June 1-3
  - The Renaissance, 1973
    Nigerian newspaper published daily, except Sundays. Contains issues number 284 (June 2, 1973) and 285 (June 4, 1973).
  - Al-Shurṭī, 1978 December, 1980 March
  - Al-Siasi, 1978 December
  - Sunday Punch, 1973 June 3
    Sunday edition of the Nigerian newspaper The Punch.
  - Syrian poster warning against the Muslim Brothers, 1981
  - Al-Talib, 1980 March
  - Al-'Usbue al-Thaqafi, 1976 October, 1978 December 15
  - Voice of Masr, 1973 October 6
    In Arabic. Printed in Jersey City, New Jersey.
  - Al-Zahf al-Akhdar, 1980 March 3 and 10